ANS Record Group 2: Curatorial, 1858-ongoing
ANS Archives
- Series 10: George C. Miles curator correspondence, research materials, and lectures, 1933 - 1974; 3 cubic feet (4 boxes)
  - Box 1 of 5 - Correspondence
    - Azizbeglou, M.
    - Bloesch, Hansjoerg.
    - Bosworth, C. E.
    - Brown, Helen Mitchell
    - Bruckner, Geraldine (University Museum, University of Pennsylvania)
    - Brunner, Christopher
    - Burn, Richard (Sir)
    - Caley, Earle R.
    - Coolidge, John (Fogg Art Museum)
    - Cora collection
    - Curiel, Raoul
    - DeShazo, A. S.
    - Dols, Michael
    - Encyclopedia Persica
    - Erdmann, Kurt
    - Ettinghausen, Richard F.
    - Fahmy, Abd al-Rahman.
    - Farrugia de Candia, M. J.
    - Faure, Paul
    - Fitzwilliam Museum
    - Freeman, Sarah
    - Frye, Richard G.
    - Garcia-Gomez, E.
    - Ghirshman, Roman
    - Gibb, H. A. R.
    - Goodrich, L. Carrington
    - Glidden, Harold W.
    - Göbl, Robert
    - Grabar, Oleg
    - Grierson, Philip
    - Gropp, G.
    - Grohmann, Adolf
    - Gurnet, Robert
    - Jungfleisch, M.
    - Lane-Poole, Austin
    - Leuthold, Enrique
    - Levi Della Vida, G.
    - Levy, S.
    - Lopez, R. S.
    - Luther, Kenneth A.M.
    - Mackenzie, Franklin
    - Mateu y Llopis, Philipe
    - Morton, A. H.
    - Mottahedeh, Roy P.
    - Murraciole, P.
    - Moutsopoulos, N. C.
    - Marinho, Jose R.
    - Minorsky, V.
    - Madelung, Wilfred
    - Morris, Robert W.
    - Nahapetian, Yervand
    - Pereire, Roger
    - Poladian, Armenak
    - Schmidt, Erich
    - Walker, John
    - Assorted
  - Box 2 of 5 - Lectures and Photographs
    - Lecture outlines, 1959-1964
    - Lectures, 1952
    - Lectures, 1952-1956
    - Lectures, 1953-1954
    - Lectures, 1959
    - Lecture: Islamic numismatics, 1946
    - Lecture: Archaeology – Millbrook School, 1952
    - Lecture: Numismatic crossroad, 1952
    - Lecture: Numismatics as a field of study, 1955
    - Lecture: Crete, 1956-1971
    - Lecture: The role of coins in history, 1957
    - Lecture: Arabs in Greece?, 1959
    - Lecture: Islam and Byzantium, a numismatic commentary, 1959 (revised 1961 and 1965)
    - Lectures: Byzantines and Arabs, 1963
    - Lecture: The role of numismatics in archaeology, 1963-1965
    - Lecture: St. Paul’s Travels
    - Lecture: Traces of the Arabs in Greece, 1965
    - Lecture: A bird’s-eye view of Greek coins, 1972
    - Lecture: Survival of Sasonian motifs, 1973
    - Photographs: Abu Sa’id coin
    - Photographs: Egyptian weights (1 of 2)
    - Photographs: Egyptian weights (2 of 2)
    - Photographs: pasted plates of A Catalog of the Palace Collection of Ancient Coins and Bronzes by Imperial Order, Shizheng, et al.
  - Box 3 of 5 - Research Materials
    - “Numismatica Hispanica” [Hispanic numismatic series?] proposal.
    - Abdullah
    - Abbasid Partisan
    - Ahnas/Misr
    - Ali b. Isa
    - Arabs in Crete – Arabic Sources
    - Arab Imitations of Byzantine AE of Alexandria
    - Arab Sasanians, New
    - Armenian Gold Ring
    - A------- hoard
    - Atabeg coins – Photos
    - Atabeg coins – Prototypes
    - Behbud
    - Dirham
    - Dirhem hoard
    - Dune hoard – Stockholm
    - Dirhems, Oversized – Now ANS
    - Dulafids, Abu
    - Egyptian Damqhas – Hall-marks
    - Earliest Arab gold coinage
    - Early Arab Dinars
    - Ghayunavid hoard
    - Istakhr – tables
    - Istakhr – photographs
    - Islamic numismatics
    - Kakwayhid hoard
    - Kakwayhids
    - Kekova coins
    - Kevorkian collection
    - Kharijite dirham – ‘Ubaydah al-Taghlibi
    - Lead seals
    - Masabadhan
    - Mihrab, ‘Anazah and ‘Alam (paper read at AOS in 1949, plus research notes)
    - Misr mint – rare Abbasids
    - Mousa Settareh hoard
    - Muzaffarids
    - Nishapur
    - Normans of Sicily
    - Persepolis - NR
    - Persepolis – Islamic inscriptions
    - Persepolis - Tall-i-Bakun
    - Rayy – Luristan notes, 1934
    - Rayy – Luristan miscellaneous correspondence
    - Rayy – numismatics, 1934-1936
    - Rayy – 1934-1936
    - Rayy – Oriental Institute
    - Rayy – Parthian hoard
    - Rayy – miscellaneous notes
    - Salgharid medallion
    - Samarra mint
    - Sasanian metrology
    - Seljuq coins in the ANS
    - Shahs of Persia
    - Counterstamped Turkish AE
    - Turkoman Song
    - Unpublished early tombstones
    - Ziyarids
    - Assorted
    - Binder: History of the Crusades, correspondence, including of Michael Bates, 1970s, 1980s
  - Box 4 of 5 - Index card set
    - Rayy history and names of persons
  - Box 5 of 5 - Index card set
    - Visigoths
- Series 11: Henry Grunthal curator correspondence, 1967-1969; 2 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Rubbings (Visual works); Correspondence; Grunthal, Henry, 1905-2001
  Contains official correspondence from Grunthal's work as curator at the American Numismatic Society, primarily letters between Grunthal and his colleagues and members of the American Numismatic Society (ANS), coin collectors, and the general public about the cost and historical values of coins, medals, and paper money. The letters also include queries about the identification of coins and potential acquisitions, visits to the ANS, and the recommendation of dealers. Some queries were passed along to the ANS from other organizations, such as universities and galleries. Answers to queries include identification summaries, estimated values, and sources to consult. The collection includes both the letter received and the letter sent and occasionally coin rubbings. Letters are from all over the world, including Hong Kong, Canada, Tasmania, West Bengal India, Toronto, Singapore, Malaysia, Nicaragua, Uganda, England and Italy.
  Henry Grunthal (1905-2001) of the Riverdale section of the Bronx in New York City was born in Cologne, Germany, and was the son of numismatist and medal publisher Hugo Grunthal. He joined the American Numismatic Society (ANS) staff in 1953 as assistant to the chief curator and moved up to the position of curator of European and modern coins, a position he held until his retirement in 1973. His main activities at the ANS were building, labeling, and organizing the collections and assisting members with the identification and appraisal of coins, paper money, and medals. He was educated at the Friedrich Wilhelm University in Berlin, the University of Jena, and at the Sorbonne in Paris, where he studied archaeology and art history. He also studied numismatics under Kurt Regling in Berlin and Geheimrat Pick in Gotha. In 1938 he emigrated to the United States from Germany to work for Stack's Rare Coins in New York City. After retirement he was an independent numismatic consultant in New York City, where he also conducted auctions with Edward Gans at Numismatic Fine Arts. He wrote several articles for publications such as The Numismatist and Coin World and co-authored two books, Carolingian Coinage and The Coinage of Peru. He was awarded the American Numismatic Association Medal of Merit in 1970. Grunthal also received an ANS medal marking fifty years of continuous membership in 1979. He had been a member of the American Numismatic Association since 1929 and was active in both the Bronx Coin Club and the New York Numismatic Club, both of which he served as president.
  - Box 1 of 2: 1967-1968
  - Box 2 of 2: 1969
- Series 12: Michael L. Bates curator correspondence and coin photographs, 1958-2004; 5 cubic feet (5 boxes)
  Islamic coin mentioned in Shraga Qedar, July 5, 1984, found in collection. Removed March 1, 2012, given to collection manager Stolyarie. Efforts being made to contact Qedar.
  Some files are in alphabetical order; others are chronologically arranged.
  Correspondence; Invitations; Announcements; Floor plans; Bates, Michael L., 1941-; Miles, George Carpenter, 1904-1975
  Contains correspondence relating to Bates’s activities as a curator of Islamic coins at the American Numismatic Society. Includes discussions of coins with scholars and collectors, though some inquiries from the general public are also present. Topics include coin photograph orders; the selling of information from the ANS computerized database at one cent per coin; the receipt and review of articles and research papers; seminar student applications; and gifts of coins to the ANS. A letter from Hussah al-Sabah expresses sorrow for the September 11, 2001, attack on New York (H, Box 2). In addition to the letters, there are memorandums on such policies and procedures as processing cast orders, loan requests, authentication services, removal of high-value coins, goals and priorities, purchase of duplicates by staff members, the Society’s work day, property in bank storage, and security. Also present are floor plans and other items relating to the Society’s move to Williams Street (1999-2003); ephemera such as event invitations and announcements; and 0.5 cubic feet of coin photographs relating to the publication Greek, Roman, and Islamic coins, from Sardis (1981) by T.V. Buttrey, Ann Johnston, Kenneth M. MacKenzie, and Michael L. Bates. The earliest letters, dating from 1958 and into the 1960s, before Bates joined the staff of ANS, are from files originally kept by Islamic numismatist George C. Miles, chief curator and executive director of the ANS.
  Michael L. Bates was born in Louisville, Kentucky, in 1941. He obtained bachelor (1963) and doctorate (1975) degrees from the University of Chicago, with his education and research culminating in his dissertation, Yemen and Its Conquest by the Ayyubids of Egypt (A.D. 1137-1202). He served as assistant curator (1970-1972), associate curator (1972-1977), and curator of Islamic coins (1977-2004), with his thirty-four year term of service as an ANS curator being the longest in the Society’s history. A major undertaking of Bates’s early years at ANS was the sorting and attributing of what were believed to be nearly 2,000 thirteenth-century Ayyubid silver dirhams, a hoard the ANS purchased in 1971, with nearly a third of the coins found to be Crusader imitations. Bates then turned his attention to studying coins of the Umayyad caliphate (661-750), and was granted a National Endowment for the Arts fellowship to travel to England and France to further study them. In 1978, 1980, and 1982-1983, he served as a coin expert at the American excavations at Fustat, the oldest Islamic section of Cairo. He was first elected a member of the International Numismatic Commission (INC) in 1979, and in addition to publishing on a variety of topics, Bates also organized educational seminars at ANS on topics such as collecting Islamic coins and the Arab-Sasanian coinage of Iran.
  - Box 1 of 5
    - ANS administration, 1966-1988
    - ANS goals and priorities, 1985
    - ANS history, 1999-2000
    - ANS staff policies, 1973
    - ANS Islamic committee, 1976-1981
    - ANS security, 1980-1986
    - ANS Williams Street, 2003
    - ANS Ephemera - 2003
    - ANS Ephemera - Gala, 2004
    - Dawn Bennett – Curatorial assistant, 2001
    - Paul Balog obituary drafts, 1982
    - Non-scholarly, 1995
    - Correspondence, 1996
    - Choukri Heddouchi, 1997
    - Shaykh Hamad Fellowship, 1996-2000
    - Robert W. Morris collection, 1970-2004
    - International Numismatic Congress, 1991
    - International Numismatic Congress – Islamic Workshop, 1991
    - Islamic Committee, 1998-1999
    - Islamic Committee prize, 1994-1996
    - South Asian and Central Asian Committee, 1998
    - Sasanian Iran conference, 2003
    - Segovia Mint, 1988-1992
    - Fundraising campaign, 1999-2000
    - American Oriental Society, 1976
    - Henri Arroyo, 1974-1980
    - E. Ashtor, 1975-1981
    - Henri Awad Amin, 1982-1984
    - Bruce McGowan, 1986
    - Miquel Barcelo, 1975-1990
    - Anna M. Balaguer, 1975-1981
    - Pratipal Bhatia, 1975-1985
    - Herbert L. Bodman, Jr., 1971-1983
    - C.E. Bosworth, 1975-1981
    - Bruce B. Braun, 1972-1974
    - Joseph J. Brennig, 1975-1978
    - Michael R. Broome, 1974-1989
    - Helen Mitchell Brown, 1974-1980
    - Colin R. Bruce, 1972-1984
    - Richard Bulliet, 1971-1983
    - Marcel Burstein, 1972-1975
    - Claude Cahen, 1979-1985
    - R.A.G. Carson, 1977-1984
    - Christmas cards, 1974
    - Raoul Curiel, 1972-1981
    - S.D. Goitein, 1958-1979
    - Oleg Grabar, 1975-1978
    - Gilles Hennequin, 1975-1985
    - William D. Holberton, 1972-1978
    - Dickran Kouymjian, 1972-1983
    - Roger Kuntz, 1973-1986
    - INC (International Numismatic Commission), 1985
    - INC (International Numismatic Commission), 1986
    - INC (International Numismatic Commission), 1987
    - INC (International Numismatic Commission), 1988
    - INC (International Numismatic Commission), 1989
    - INC (International Numismatic Commission)—Computer, 1988
    - INC (International Numismatic Commission), 1991
  - Box 2 of 5
    - Ahmad Ajaj, 2003
    - A, 1980-2002
    - Stephen Album, 1972-1996
    - C.A. Azami, 1961-1980
    - B (1), 1996-2002
    - B (2), 1991-1996
    - C, 1984-2003
    - Country agents, 1993
    - Joseph Lamar Daniels, 1999
    - D (1), 1990-2002
    - D (2), 1990-1993
    - E, 1983-2000
    - F, 1991-2000
    - G, 1983-2002
    - Robert C. Grossman – Obituary, 1994
    - H, 1991-2000
    - Richard Simon Hanson, 1973-1976
    - Raymond Herbert, 1963-1985
    - David Hollenberg – Summer Seminar, 2001 **Closed file - **Personal data**
    - Jesse Holzer, 2000
    - I, 1979-1999
    - Miguel Ibanez, 1997
    - Lutz Ilisch, 1992-1996
    - J, 1991-2002
    - K, 1990-2001
    - L, 1983-1999
    - Roger deWardt Lane, 2003
    - Nicholas Lowick, 1971-1986
    - M, 1983-2000
    - Mark Metzler, 1999
    - Manzoor Mirza, 1992-1999
  - Box 3 of 5
    - N, 1994-1999
    - O, 1992-2000
    - Richard Parker, 1998
    - Marc-Henri Pelletier, 1999-2002
    - Shraga Qedar, 1976-1999
    - R, 1980-2000
    - Gert Rispling, 1990-1994
    - S (1), 1991-2002
    - S (2), 1973-1989
    - Elizabeth Sanders, 1992-1996
    - Stuart D. Sears, 1989-1996
    - R.C. Senior, 1981-1991
    - Samir Shamma, 1972-1999
    - William F. Spengler, 1990-1999
    - T, 1991-2000
    - Deborah Tor, 1999
    - Susan Tyler-Smith, 1979-1995
    - U, 1976-2002
    - Abul Faraj Al-‘Ush, 1965-1984
    - V, 1977-1995
    - W, 1973-2001
    - William Warden, 1972-1999
    - C.M. Webdale, 1974-1980
    - Ernst-Günther Weber, 1970-1973
    - H. Bartlett Wells, 1976-1980
    - Donald Whitcomb, 1975-1988
    - Robert Wicks, 1977-1987
    - Y, 1979-2001
  - Box 4 of 5
    - 1984-1985
    - 1986, A-F
    - 1986, G-P
    - 1986, Q-Z
    - 1987, A-D
    - 1987, E-K
    - 1987, L-R
    - 1987, S-Z
    - 1988, A-G
    - 1988, H-R
    - 1988, S-Z
    - 1989, A-E
    - 1989, F-M
    - 1989, N-Z
    - 1990, A-N
    - 1990, O-Z
  - Box 5 of 5
    - 1991, A-P
    - 1991, R-Z
    - 1992
    - 1992, A-G
    - 1992, H-P
    - 1992, R-Z
    - Robert L. Saxe and Marie Saxe gifts (1995.44, 1995.45), 1994
    - Coin photographs relating to the publication Greek, Roman, and Islamic coins, from Sardis (1981) by T.V. Buttrey, Ann Johnston, Kenneth M. MacKenzie, and Michael L. Bates.
    - 1 videocassette, 2003
- Series 13: Jeremiah D. Brady curator correspondence, 1916 - 1981; 0.7 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Correspondence; Photographs; Brady, Jeremiah, 1940-; Ebsen, Buddy, 1908-2003; Goetz, Karl, 1875-1950; O'Sullivan, Frank; Appleton, Arthur; Eliscu, Frank, 1912-1996
  Jeremiah Brady (b. 1940), originally of Fall River, Massachusetts, obtained a bachelor’s degree from Harvard College (1961), an M.Litt. from Cambridge University (1963), and a Ph.D. in medieval history from Harvard (1972). He served as assistant (1970) then associate (1972) curator of medieval coins at ANS until 1980, when he left to take a position with Sotheby Parke-Bernet. During his years with the ANS, Brady was responsible for numerous projects in addition to his normal curatorial work, including the mounting the exhibit “Coinage of the Americas” for the 1973 International Numismatic Congress, coordinating the commissioning of the 1977 ANS members medal, and authoring Sylloge of Coins of the British Isles.
  Appears to be mostly materials relating to his position as secretary of the ANS standing committee on medals (1973-1976) and medals and decorations (1977-1980). There are correspondence, photographs, and other items having to do with a competition for a new design for a member’s medal in 1977, including photographs of plaster models and design critiques by committee and jury members of Frank Eliscu’s winning design. Also present are materials relating to additions to the Society’s collection of medals by Karl Goetz, such as a donation by Christian “Buddy” Ebson (1979) and correspondence on Goetz’s Lusitania medal, which includes the earliest item in the series, a J. Schulman invoice listing a Goetz medal (1916); correspondence relating to a legal matter arising over the attribution of a possibly imitation Davis Guard medal commemorating the Civil War battle of Sabine Pass (1974-1975); and files on donations from Frank O’Sullivan (1979.60) and Arthur Appleton (1978.64). There are three notebooks of materials (1976-1979) relating to a project relating to the documentation of all medals issued by the ANS since its founding in 1858. The notebooks contain completed forms with information on the medals, some correspondence, and photocopies from published sources as well as circulars (fliers) for some of the medals, such as Ernest Babelon (1912), Declaration of War (1917), and Catskill Aqueduct (1917), Prince of Wales (1919), and Centennial (1958).
  - Box 1 of 2
    - Member’s medal – Competition rules, jury, fact sheets, etc., 1976
    - Member’s medal – Medal committee and jury letters on Frank Eliscu’s design, 1977
    - Member’s medal – All artists – Pre-April, 1977
    - Member’s medal – Eliscu photographs, 1977
    - Member’s medal – Eliscu correspondence, 1977
    - Member’s medal – Jury – Pre-Eliscu, 1976-1977
    - Karl Goetz medals – Superior Stamp – Buddy Ebsen collection of Karl Goetz, 1979
    - Karl Goetz medals – Robert Sillins collection, 1978
    - Karl Goetz medals – Lawrence S. Goldberg, 1978
    - Karl Goetz medals – Inquiries pending, 1979
    - Karl Goetz medals – Including Lusitania, 1916, 1981
    - Karl Goetz medals – ANS photographs
    - Karl Goetz medals – Duplicates, 1979
    - Karl Goetz medals, 1980
    - Sylloge of Coins of the British Isles – Draft with coin photograph plates (2 folders)
    - Frank O’Sullivan gift (1979.60), 1978
    - Arthur Appleton gift (1978.64), 1978
    - Jørgen Steen Jensen, 1978
    - Sabine Pass – Davis Guard medal, 1974-1975
  - Box 2 of 2
    - Three notebooks on ANS medals
- Series 14: Nancy M. Waggoner curator correspondence and other material, 1968-1989; 1.5 cubic feet (2 boxes)
  Waggoner, Nancy M., 1924-1989; Gans, Edward, 1887-1991; Mirza, H.H.; Kelley, Robert F., 1894-1976; Lindren, Henry; Correspondence; Notes; Lectures
  Nancy M. Waggoner (1924-1989) graduated from Smith College (B.A., 1946) before attending Columbia University (M.A., 1963; Ph.D., 1968), where she studied under Margaret Thompson in the first seminar in numismatics, which ultimately resulted in her dissertation on the mint of Alexander the Great at Babylon. She served ANS as assistant curator (1968) and curator (1976) of Greek Coins and took over the Columbia seminar when Margaret Thompson retired in 1979. She remained at ANS until her retirement in 1988 and died the following year. After her death, the ANS held a symposium in her honor, which resulted in the publication in 1991 of Mnemata: Papers in Memory of Nancy M. Waggoner. Her two major publications were: Archaic Greek Silver Coinage. The “Asyut” Hoard, which she co-authored with Martin Price, and Early Greek Coins in the Collection of Jonathan P. Rosen, a volume in the Society’s ACNAC (American Coins in North American Collections) series. In addition, Waggoner supervised the publication of three volumes of the Society’s contribution to the Sylloge Nummorum Graecorum.
  Contains correspondence (1981-1988) on a variety of topics relating to her work as curator of Greek coins at the American Numismatic Society, including letters mostly with other scholars, but also with the general public, discussing the study of coins and their identification, attribution, and sometimes value, occasionally with coin photographs included. Also present are letters of recommendation and introduction written for others; correspondence and other materials relating to the development of ANS collections, such as an appraisal and articles relating to the Robert F. Kelley bequest (1977) and letters relating to the possible availability of coins from the H.H. Mirza (1983) and Henry Lindren (1984) collections; a report, procedures, and other materials having to do with the ANS photo file (photofile) (1980); a letter from Edward Gans on the history of his collecting and how he “abandoned the collecting of coins,” having lost his wife and his vision (1985); an agreement form concerning materials from Athos Moretti on temporary deposit at ANS (1986); notes, research letters, and materials relating to her efforts in 1974 to build upon her 1968 dissertation on a die-study of the Alexander mint at Babylon; and session lectures and student papers from the seminar she taught at Columbia University (1982-1989).
  - Box 1 of 2
    - Babylon research, 1971-1975
    - Catalog additions, 1968-1970
    - Iraq hoard, 1973-1977
    - Babylon correspondence, 1969-1975
    - Waggoner – Numismatics (green binder), 1970-1975
    - Constantin A. Marinescu – Byzantium, 1985
    - Fasti Archaeologici, 1985-1989
    - Zervos – Ptolemy I – Satrapal - The Bronze
    - Zervos – Ptolemy I – Conspectus – Typed notes
    - Joseph B. Scholten – Dissertation, 1987-1988
    - Philip II – Attic-weight drachms from a private collection – Photographs
    - Photo file, 1980
    - Popular Archaeology magazine, 1972-1975
    - Lecture – Numismatic terms and techniques, 1984
    - American Philosophical Society grant, 1970
    - William P. Wallace collection, 1976-1980
    - Alexander – Lectures, 1968
    - Robert F. Kelley bequest, 1977
    - ANS – SNG (Sylloge Nummorum Graecorum) – International, 1983
    - Talks – London symposium, 1987-1988
    - Talks – Royal Numismatic Society, 1984-1985
    - Talks - McGill University, 1973
    - Marinescu – Calchedon – Koch deposit, 1987-1988
    - Halicarnassus, 1988
    - Bibliography and notes
    - Columbia seminar
    - Columbia seminar – Session lectures
    - Columbia University seminar, 1982
    - Columbia University seminar, 1984
    - Columbia University seminar, 1987
    - Columbia University seminar, 1989
    - Summer seminar
  - Box 2 of 2
    - Correspondence, 1977-1978
    - Correspondence, 1981
    - Correspondence, 1982
    - Correspondence, 1983
    - Correspondence, 1984
    - Correspondence, 1985
    - Correspondence, 1986
    - Correspondence, 1987
    - Correspondence, 1988
- Series 15: Alan M. Stahl curator correspondence and other material, 1914-2000, bulk 1982-2000; 13 cubic feet (13 boxes)
  Though some patterns can be discerned, the materials are unarranged. This disorder may have been the result of the packing and unpacking of the records during one of the Society’s physical relocations that took place after Stahl’s departure.
  Jovine, Marcel, 1921-2003; Brenner, Victor D. (Victor David), 1871-1924; Morgan, J. P. (John Pierpont), 1867-1943; Jovine, Marcel, 1921-2003; Correspondence; Notes; Memorandums; Photographs; Designs (Concepts); Fédération internationale de la médaille; American Medallic Sculpture Association